When I go to parties,
عندما أذهب الى الحفلات
it doesn't usually take very long
عادة لا يستغرق الكثير من الوقت
for people to find out
ليكتشف الناس
that I'm a scientist and I study sex.
أنني عالمة وأنني ادرسُ الجنس
And then I get asked questions.
ومن ثم يتم سؤالي العديد من الأسئلة
And the questions usually have a very particular format.
والأسئلة تتخذ عادة نموذج معين
They start with the phrase,
يبدأون بعبارة,
"A friend told me,"
"اخبرني صديق"
and then they end with the phrase,
وينتهون بعبارة,
"Is this true?"
"هل هذا صحيح؟"
And most of the time
وفي معظم الوقت
I'm glad to say that I can answer them,
اكون سعيدة بالقول انني يمكنني اجابتهم
but sometimes I have to say,
لكن بعض الأحيان علي القول,
"I'm really sorry,
"انا متأسفة,
but I don't know
لكنني لا أعرف
because I'm not that kind of a doctor."
لانني لست ذلك النوع من الاطباء"
That is, I'm not a clinician,
أي أنني لست طبيبة,
I'm a comparative biologist who studies anatomy.
أنا عالمة احياء مقارنة, أقوم بدراسة علم التشريح.
And my job is to look at lots of different species of animals
ووظيفتي هي النظر في الكثير من الأنواع المختلفة من الاحياء
and try to figure out how their tissues and organs work
ومحاولة فهم كيف تعمل اعضاؤها وأنسجتها
when everything's going right,
عندما يكون كل شيء على ما يرام,
rather than trying to figure out
بدلاً من محاولة فهم
how to fix things when they go wrong,
كيف يمكن اصلاح الاشياء عندما لا تعمل,
like so many of you.
كالكثير منكم.
And what I do is I look for similarities and differences
وما اقوم به هو ملاحظة أوجه الشبه والفروقات
in the solutions that they've evolved
في الحلول التي طورتها الكائنات
for fundamental biological problems.
للمشاكل البيولوجية الأساسية.
So today I'm here to argue
اليوم ان هنا لمناقشة
that this is not at all
انا هذا ليس على الاطلاق
an esoteric Ivory Tower activity
نشاط مقتصر على الأبراج العاجية
that we find at our universities,
كالذي نجده في الجامعات,
but that broad study
لكنه دراسة واسعة
across species, tissue types and organ systems
في الأنواع ,الانسجة, وانظمة الاعضاء
can produce insights
يمكن ان تنتج رؤى
that have direct implications for human health.
لها تأثير مباشر على صحة الانسان
And this is true both of my recent project
وذلك صحيح في مشروعي الحالي
on sex differences in the brain,
حول فروقات الجنس في الدماغ,
and my more mature work
وعملي المتخصص
on the anatomy and function of penises.
حول تشريح وعمل الاعضاء التناسلية الذكرية
And now you know why I'm fun at parties.
وتعلمون الان لما انا محبوبة في الحفلات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So today I'm going to give you an example
اليوم سوف اعطيكم مثالاً
drawn from my penis study
مأخوذ من دراستي حول العضو التناسلي الذكري
to show you how knowledge
لأعرض لكم كيف ان المعرفة
drawn from studies of one organ system
المأخوذة من الدراسات حول نظام عضو معين
provided insights into a very different one.
تقدم رؤى لعضو اخر مختلف
Now I'm sure as everyone in the audience already knows --
أنا الان متأكدة أن كل شخص من الحضور يعرف--
I did have to explain it to my nine-year-old late last week --
شرحت ذلك لابني ذو التسعة اعوام في الاسبوع الماضي--
penises are structures that transfer sperm
الاعضاء التناسلية الذكرية هي هياكل تقوم بنقل السائل المنوي
from one individual to another.
من طرف الى اخر
And the slide behind me
والصور خلفي
barely scratches the surface
تظهر بوضوح
of how widespread they are in animals.
مدى تنوعها وانتشارها في الحيوانات.
There's an enormous amount of anatomical variation.
هناك كم هائل من التنوعات التشريحية
You find muscular tubes, modified legs, modified fins,
تجد الانابيب العضلية,الارجل المعدلة,الزعانف المعدلة,
as well as the mammalian fleshy, inflatable cylinder
وكذلك في الثديات,الاسطوانات المنفوخة
that we're all familiar with --
والتي نحن معتادون عليها--
or at least half of you are.
او على الأقل نصفكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think we see this tremendous variation
أعتقد أننا نرى هذا التنوع الهائل
because it's a really effective solution
لانه حقاً حلٌ فعّالٌ
to a very basic biological problem,
لمشكلة بايولوجية اساسية
and that is getting sperm in a position
وهي ان نوصل السائل المنوي الى المكان
to meet up with eggs and form zygotes.
لكي يقابل البويضات ويكون البويضات الملقحة.
Now the penis isn't actually required for internal fertiliztion,
العضو التناسلي في الواقع غير مطلوب في الاخصاب الداخلي
but when internal fertilization evolves,
لكن عندما يتطور الاخصاب الداخلي
penises often follow.
يتبعه عادة العضو التناسلي الذكري.
And the question I get when I start talking about this most often is,
والسؤال الذي يُطرح عليّ عندما أبدأ الحديث عن هذا الموضوع عادةً هو
"What made you interested in this subject?"
"مالذي يجعلك مهتمه بهذا الموضوع؟"
And the answer is skeletons.
والجواب هو الهياكل.
You wouldn't think that skeletons and penises
ربما لا تعتقد ان الهياكل والأعضاء التناسلية الذكرية
have very much to do with one another.
لديها الكثير لتقدمه لبعضها البعض
And that's because we tend to think of skeletons
وذلك لأننا نتجه للأعتقاد ان الهياكل
as stiff lever systems
انها انظمة رفع صلبة
that produce speed or power.
تنتج السرعة والقوة.
And my first forays into biological research,
وأول غزواتي في الأبحاث البيولوجية,
doing dinosaur paleontology as an undergraduate,
هو حول الديناصورات المتحجرة كمشروع للتخرج
were really squarely in that realm.
كان بصراحة في تلك المملكة.
But when I went to graduate school to study biomechanics,
ولكن بعد التخرج اتجهت الى دراسة الميكانيكا الحيوية "بيو ميكانيك"
I really wanted to find a dissertation project
اردت ان اجد اطروحة بحث
that would expand our knowledge of skeletal function.
تقوم بتوسيع معرفتنا حول وظيفة الهيكل
I tried a bunch of different stuff.
بحثت في الكثير من الاشياء المختلفة
A lot of it didn't pan out.
لكن الكثير منها لم يكن موفقاً
But then one day I started thinking
لكن في أحد الأيام بدأت في التفكير
about the mammalian penis.
حول الأعضاء التناسلية الذكرية في الثديات.
And it's really an odd sort of structure.
وهو حقاً تكوين عجيب.
Before it can be used for internal fertilization,
قبل ان يستخدم للأخصاب الداخلي,
its mechanical behavior has to change
سلوكه الميكانيكي يجب ان يتغير
in a really dramatic fashion.
بصورة دراماتيكية.
Most of the time it's a flexible organ.
في معظم الاوقات هو عضو مرن.
It's easy to bend.
ينحني بسهولة.
But before it's brought into use
لكن قبل ان يتم استخدامه
during copulation
خلال الجماع
it has to become rigid,
يجب ان يكون صلباً
it has to become difficult to bend.
ويصبح من الصعب ان ينحني.
And moreover, it has to work.
وعلاوة على ذلك يجب ان يعمل.
A reproductive system that fails to function
الجهاز التناسلي الذي يفشل في القيام بعمله
produces an individual that has no offspring,
ينتج فرداً بدون ذرية,
and that individual is then kicked out of the gene pool.
وذلك الفرد يُلقى خارجا من النظام الجيني.
And so I thought, "Here's a problem
بالتالي فكرت "هنا مشكلة
that just cries out for a skeletal system --
تصرخ لأجل نظام هيكلي--
not one like this one,
ليس شيء يشبه هذا,
but one like this one --
لكن شيء يشبه هذا--
because, functionally,
لانه عمليا,
a skeleton is any system
الهيكل هو اي نظام
that supports tissue and transmits forces.
يدعم الانسجة وينقل القوى.
And I already knew that animals like this earthworm,
و أعلم ان حيوانات مثل دودة الارض هذه,
indeed most animals,
وفي الواقع جميع الحيوانات,
don't support their tissues
لا تدعم انسجتها
by draping them over bones.
عن طريق لفها حول عظام.
Instead they're more like reinforced water balloons.
بدلاً من ذلك هي تشابه بالونات المياه المعززة.
They use a skeleton that we call a hydrostatic skeleton.
تستخدم هياكل نسميها "هياكل هيدرو ستاتيكية"
And a hydrostatic skeleton
والهياكل الهيدرو ستاتيكية
uses two elements.
تستخدم عنصرين.
The skeletal support comes from an interaction
الدعم الهيكلي القادم من التفاعل
between a pressurized fluid
بين السائل المضغوط
and a surrounding wall of tissue
والجدار المحيط من النسيج
that's held in tension and reinforced with fibrous proteins.
والذي يجتمع في التوتر والبروتينات الليفية المعززة
And the interaction is crucial.
والتفاعل حاسم.
Without both elements you have no support.
بدون العنصرين لا يوجد هناك دعم.
If you have fluid
اذا كان لديك سائل
with no wall to surround it
بدون جدار يحيط به
and keep pressure up,
وتواصل ضغطه,
you have a puddle.
يكون لديك عجينة.
And if you have just the wall
واذا كان لديك جدار فقط
with no fluid inside of it to put the wall in tension,
بدون سائل داخله ليجعل الجدار في توتر.
you've got a little wet rag.
يكون لديك خرقة مبللولة.
When you look at a penis in cross section,
عندما تنظر الى مقطع عرضي للعضو التناسلي الذكري,
it has a lot of the hallmarks
لديه الكثير من سمات
of a hydrostatic skeleton.
الهيكل الهيدروستاتيكي.
It has a central space
لديه فضاء مركزي
of spongy erectile tissue
من النسيج الاسفنجي المنتصب
that fills with fluid -- in this case blood --
والمملؤ بالسائل -- الدم في هذه الحالة--
surrounded by a wall of tissue
محاط بجدار من النسيج
that's rich in a stiff structural protein called collagen.
والغني ببروتين هيكلي صلب يُسمى "الكولاجين".
But at the time when I started this project,
لكن في الوقت الذي بدأت في هذا المشروع,
the best explanation I could find for penal erection
التفسير الوحيد الذي استطعت ايجاده لانتصاب العضو التناسلي الذكري
was that the wall surrounded these spongy tissues,
ان الجدار المحيط بتلك الانسجة الاسفنجية,
and the spongy tissues filled with blood
وتلك الانسجة الاسفنجية تمتلئ بالدم
and pressure rose and voila! it became erect.
ويزداد الضغط وذلك كل شيء ! يُصبح منتصباً
And that explained to me expansion --
وذلك فسر لي التمدد--
made sense: more fluid, you get tissues that expand --
المفهوم كالتالي: كلما زاد السائل, تتمدد الأنسجة--
but it didn't actually explain erection.
لكن ذلك في الواقع لا يفسر الانتصاب.
Because there was no mechanism in this explanation
لأنه لا يوجد اّلية في هذا التفسير
for making this structure hard to bend.
والتي تجعل هذا الهيكل صعب الانحناء.
And no one had systematically looked at the wall tissue.
ولم ينظر احد من قبل بشكل منهجي في جدار النسيج.
So I thought, wall tissue's important in skeletons.
لذلك اعتقدت ان جدار النسيج مهم في الهياكل.
It has to be part of the explanation.
سوف يكون جزء من التفسير.
And this was the point
وتلك هي النقطة
at which my graduate adviser said,
التي قال فيها مشرف التخرج,
"Whoa! Hold on. Slow down."
"تمهلي, ابطئي قليلاً"
Because after about six months of me talking about this,
لأنه بعد ستة اشهر من الحديث حول هذا,
I think he finally figured out
اعتقد أنه اخيراً لاحظ
that I was really serious about the penis thing.
انني جادة بالفعل حول معضلة العضو التناسلي الذكري.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So he sat me down, and he warned me.
لذلك أجلسني , وحذرني.
He was like, "Be careful going down this path.
كان لسان حاله ," كوني حذرة من الانحدار في هذا الطريق.
I'm not sure this project's going to pan out."
لستُ مُتأكداً ان هذا المشروع سوف ينجح."
Because he was afraid I was walking into a trap.
لأنه كان يخشى انني اتجه نحو مصيدة.
I was taking on a socially embarrassing question
كنت أخذ سؤال اجتماعي مُحرج
with an answer that he thought
له إجابة كان يظن انها
might not be particularly interesting.
عملياً غير مهمة بحد ذاتها
And that was because
وذلك بسبب
every hydrostatic skeleton
ان كل هيكل هيدروستاتيكي
that we had found in nature up to that point
وجدناه في الطبيعة حتى تلك اللحظة
had the same basic elements.
له عناصر اساسية.
It had the central fluid,
له سائل مركزي
it had the surrounding wall,
وحوله جدار محيط,
and the reinforcing fibers in the wall
والالياف المعززة في الجدار
were arranged in crossed helices
منتظمة في شكل لولبي متقاطع
around the long axis of the skeleton.
حول المحور الطولي للهيكل.
So the image behind me
الصورة خلفي
shows a piece of tissue
تظهر جزء من النسيج
in one of these cross helical skeletons
في احد تلك الهياكل اللولبية المتقاطعة
cut so that you're looking at the surface of the wall.
المقطع يُظهر سطح الجدار
The arrow shows you the long axis.
السهم يبين لكم المحور الطولي,
And you can see two layers of fibers,
وبإمكانكم رؤية طبقتين من الالياف,
one in blue and one in yellow,
احداهما بالأزرق والأخرى بالأصفر,
arranged in left-handed and right-handed angles.
منتظمة بزاوية في اتجاه اليمين واليسار.
And if you weren't just looking at a little section of the fibers,
واذا لم تكن تنظر فقط الى مقطع صغير من الالياف,
those fibers would be going in helices
تلك الالياف سوف تنتظم في لوالب
around the long axis of the skeleton --
حول المحور الطولي للهيكل--
something like a Chinese finger trap,
شيء يشبه مصيدة الاصبع الصينية,
where you stick your fingers in and they get stuck.
حيث تضع اصبعك فيها وتنحشر في الداخل.
And these skeletons have a particular set of behaviors,
وتلك الهياكل لديها مجموعة من الخصائص المعينة,
which I'm going to demonstrate in a film.
والتي سوف اعرضها في فيلم.
It's a model skeleton
إنه نموذج هيكل
that I made out of a piece of cloth
والذي صنعته من قطعة قماش
that I wrapped around an inflated balloon.
وقمت بلفه حول بالون متمدد.
The cloth's cut on the bias.
القماش قطع بانحياز
So you can see that the fibers wrap in helices,
حيث بإمكانكم رؤية الالياف ملتفة في لوالب,
and those fibers can reorient as the skeleton moves,
وتلك الالياف بامكانها اعادة التشكل عندما يتحرك الهيكل,
which means the skeleton's flexible.
مما يعني ان الهيكل مرن.
It lengthens, shortens and bends really easily
يتمدد وينكمش وينثني بسهولة
in response to internal or external forces.
مستجيبا للقوى الخارجية والداخلية.
Now my adviser's concern
كان المشرف قلقاً حيال
was what if the penile wall tissue
ماذا لو كان الجدار النسيجي للقضيب
is just the same as any other hydrostatic skeleton.
يشابه اي هيكل هايدرو ستاتيكي آخر.
What are you going to contribute?
ما المساهمة التي سوف تضيفينها؟
What new thing are you contributing
ما الجديد الذي سوف تساهمي به
to our knowledge of biology?
لما نعلمه في علم الاحياء؟
And I thought, "Yeah, he does have a really good point here."
وفكرت ," فعلاً, ان لديه نقطة جيدة في هذا المجال."
So I spent a long, long time thinking about it.
لذلك امضيت وقتاً طويل جداً افكر في هذه النقطة.
And one thing kept bothering me,
وكان شيئاً واحداً يزعجني,
and that's, when they're functioning,
وهو انه عندما تقوم بالعمل
penises don't wiggle.
الاعضاء التناسلية الذكرية لا تتذبذب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So something interesting had to be going on.
اذاً هناك شيئ مثير للاهتمام يحصل.
So I went ahead, collected wall tissue,
فواصلت ,وجمعت جدار نسيجي
prepared it so it was erect,
اعددته بحيث ينتصب,
sectioned it, put it on slides
وقطعتها ,ووضعته على شرائح
and then stuck it under the microscope to have a look,
ومن ثم وضعته تحت المجهر لأُلقي نظرة,
fully expecting to see crossed helices of collagen of some variety.
متوقعةً أن أرى مقطع لولبي من الكولاجين بتشكيلة معينة.
But instead I saw this.
لكن بدلاً من ذلك رأيت هذا.
There's an outer layer and an inner layer.
هناك طبقة داخلية وطبقة خارجية.
The arrow shows you the long axis of the skeleton.
السهم يُظهر المحور الطولي للهيكل.
I was really surprised at this.
كنت متفاجئةً تماماً بهذا.
Everyone I showed it
كل من عرضته عليه
was really surprised at this.
كان حقاً متفاجئاً.
Why was everyone surprised at this?
لمذا كان الجميع متفاجئاً بهذا؟
That's because we knew theoretically
ذلك لأنه نحن نعرف نظرياً
that there was another way
أن هناك طريقة أُخرى
of arranging fibers in a hydrostatic skeleton,
لإنتظام الالياف في الهيكل الهيدروستاتيكي,
and that was with fibers at zero degrees
وذلك بحيث تكون الالياف في زوايا مقدارها صفر
and 90 degrees to the long axis of the structure.
وزوايا مقدارها 90 درجة على على المحور الطولي للبناء.
The thing is, no one had ever seen it before in nature.
وفي الواقع لم يشاهدها احد من قبل على الطبيعة.
And now I was looking at one.
والاّن انا انظر الى احداها.
Those fibers in that particular orientation
تلك الالياف في ذلك الانتظام المعين
give the skeleton a very, very different behavior.
تعطي الهيكل سلوك مختلف جداً.
I'm going to show a model
سوف أعرض نموذج
made out of exactly the same materials.
تم صنع تماماً من نفس المواد.
So it'll be made of the same cotton cloth,
حيث انه سوف يصنع من نفس القماش القطني,
same balloon, same internal pressure.
ونفس البالون,ونفس الضغط الداخلي.
But the only difference
لكن الاختلاف الوحيد
is that the fibers are arranged differently.
ان الالياف تنتظم بصورة مختلفة.
And you'll see that, unlike the cross helical model,
وسوف تشاهدون ذلك,على خلاف نموذج اللولب المتقاطع,
this model resists extension and contraction
النموذج يُقاوم التمدد والتقلص
and resists bending.
ويُقاوم الإنثناء.
Now what that tells us
الان الذي يُخبرنا به ذلك
is that wall tissues are doing so much more
ان الجدار النسيجي يقوم بدور اكثر
than just covering the vascular tissues.
من مجرد تغليف الاوعية الدموية.
They're an integral part of the penile skeleton.
انه جزء متكامل من هيكل القضيب.
If the wall around the erectile tissue wasn't there,
لو لم يكن الجدار حول الانسجة المنتصبة موجوداً
if it wasn't reinforced in this way,
لو لم يكن معززاً بهذه الطريقة,
the shape would change,
سوف يتغير الشكل,
but the inflated penis would not resist bending,
لكن القضيب المنتصب لن يُقاوم الانثناء,
and erection simply wouldn't work.
وببساطة لن يتم الإنتصاب.
It's an observation with obvious medical applications
انها ملاحظة بتطبيقات طبية واضحة
in humans as well,
كذلك في البشر,
but it's also relevant in a broad sense, I think,
ولكنها مرتبطة ايضاً بمجالات اوسع,اعتقد,
to the design of prosthetics, soft robots,
في تصميم الاطراف الصناعية ,الروبوتات الناعمة
basically anything
بشكل عام اي شيء
where changes of shape and stiffness are important.
حيث تغيرات الشكل والصلابة مُهمة.
So to sum up:
اذاً ملخص ماسبق:
Twenty years ago,
قبل عشرين سنة مضت,
I had a college adviser tell me,
قال لي مشرف الكُلية,
when I went to the college and said,
عندما ذهبت الى الكُلية وقلت,
"I'm kind of interested in anatomy,"
"انني مُهتمة بعلم التشريح,"
they said, "Anatomy's a dead science."
قالوا لي" علم التشريح هو علم ميت."
He couldn't have been more wrong.
كان على خطأ
I really believe that we still have a lot to learn
اعتقدت حقاً ان هناك الكثير لنتعلمه
about the normal structure and function of our bodies.
حول البناء العام ووظائف اجسادنا.
Not just about its genetics and molecular biology,
ليس حول علم الاحياء الجزيئي والوراثي,
but up here in the meat end of the scale.
لكن هنا ايضاً في الجزء اللحمي.
We've got limits on our time.
لم يكن لدينا الكثير من الوقت.
We often focus on one disease,
كنا نركز دائماً على الامراض
one model, one problem,
نموذج واحد, مشكلة واحدة,
but my experience suggests
لكن تجربتي تقترح
that we should take the time
اننا يجب ان نأخذ الوقت الكافي
to apply ideas broadly between systems
لكي نطبق الافكار المنتشرة بين الأنظمة
and just see where it takes us.
وننظر الى أين سوف تأخذنا
After all, if ideas about invertebrate skeletons
بعد كل ذلك,اذا كانت الأفكار حول الهياكل اللافقرية
can give us insights
يُمكن أن تعطينا رؤى
about mammalian reproductive systems,
حول الثديات المُنجبة,
there could be lots of other wild and productive connections
لرُبما كان هناك الكثير من الروابط المُثمرة
lurking out there just waiting to be found.
رابضة هناك تنتظر من يكتشفها.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)